An average consumer is bombarded
anywhere between 3,000 and 10,000 ads
every single day. The human brain cannot
process that amount of data. So, the
brain has learned to tune out all these
ads. So, you're throwing ads at the
consumers, but they're not even noticing
it.
>> This is CMO Insider where you'll get
candid takes from marketing power
players. My name's Lara O'Reilly. I'm a
senior correspondent at Business Insider
and I'm here with a marketing legend
today. Raja Rajamannar has run marketing
at MasterCard for more than 12 years as
CMO and now he's switching into the
senior fellow role. Thank you so much
for joining us.
>> Thank you very much for having me. Much
appreciated.
>> And I wanted to start with maybe a bit
of an existential question for you,
which is
why does MasterCard do so much consumer
marketing? Often times when you get a
new credit card or a bank account, you
don't get to choose who your payments
provider is. So, I'd love to know
what that involves.
>> good question. It's in fact very
existential, right? For us as a brand,
the key thing is when you are building
your brand as MasterCard, you are a
connector.
>> Mhm.
>> So, firstly, start with the places where
consumers use their cards.
The merchant should feel confident that
when they see that this is a MasterCard
transaction, that they will get paid for
it. So, it's basically trust and
dependability and reliability. That's
from the merchant side.
Now, from the bank's side, I have to
build my niche with the bank. That A,
that this is a very, very
uh a secure, safe, efficient, and
effective network. And they need to see
value proposition beyond just pure
functional elements. But, we have to
make sure that we get enough into the
consumer's mind that when a bank gives
them that particular offering, they're
very happy. So, we don't call ourselves
as a direct to consumer uh brand. We are
a B2B2C brand. Which is we are marketing
as a business to other businesses which
market to their consumers and we try to
fill this entire
length of the chain.
>> Mhm. And as I mentioned earlier, you
were the CM CEO, I should have said, at
MasterCard for for around 12 years. And
I imagine you've you've kind of left the
brand on on quite a high, but there must
have been some challenges along the way.
And I wondered if you could talk through
maybe like one one big challenge you had
and how you overcame it. Does anything
spring to mind?
>> At the beginning, I quickly discovered
that consumers associate MasterCard
overwhelmingly as a credit card company.
They say a credit card may make me spend
money on things that they don't need and
draw me into debt or they they charge me
very high interest rates.
And that makes automatically MasterCard
brand as a negative brand.
>> Mhm. And you're a payments company.
>> We are a We are a payments technology
company. We don't do payments ourselves.
So, I said this is amazing because we
don't issue a single credit card, but
you ask a normal consumer on the street,
they say, "Yeah, MasterCard is a credit
card company. Credit card companies are
not good."
So, my biggest challenge was how do I
change that perception?
So, we started getting into areas where
we were trying to earn the consumers'
trust.
For example, we launched with a program
with Stand Up to Cancer where we said
that when we run some promotions and you
as a consumer spend at a restaurant
using MasterCard,
we will
pay a part of that or we'll give a part
of the profit that we make to Stand Up
to Cancer Foundation. Started as a
simple premise, but then it has
profound. We raised almost $75 million
so far for Stand Up to Cancer. And quite
unbelievably, that group was able to get
as many as eight drugs
through FDA approval from molecule
discovery to all the trials trials and
eventually to FDA approval. We did this
about three years back or four years
back, I can't exactly remember, but
MasterCard was one of the top four most
favorite brands. So, from a category
which is considered to be negative, to
coming to be one of the top four brands
in the country is a big deal for us.
>> And now a word from our sponsor LinkedIn
ads to talk about how to cut the ball
spend from your marketing budget.
>> Marketing leaders today are under more
pressure than ever to prove real impact
and concrete [music] business outcomes.
I'm joined by Keith Browning, director
of global brand marketing at LinkedIn
[music] to learn more. What makes
LinkedIn uniquely suited to deliver
measurable business outcomes, especially
in B2B?
>> LinkedIn is the largest professional
network in the world, so we're built for
this. We're built for B2B. So, that
means firstly being able to find the
right people. So, you know, you can
target by job title or seniority,
company, etc. But, there's also the
professional context component as well.
So, people come to LinkedIn to to learn,
to evaluate potential solutions, and
certainly to make buying decisions as
well.
>> And over your career, you've been quite
successful at kind of challenging some
of the norms, some of the kind of the
marketing playbooks or the marketing
theory that that people often lean upon
in this in this industry. I mean, one
example is you've kind of famously
declared advertising dead. And you
[laughter] at one point you cut your
advertising budget by 70%, which is kind
of unheard of. Most most marketers are
crying out for more budget each year,
not less.
>> I always think of myself as a consumer
first before I consider myself a
marketer.
As a consumer today,
do I like advertisements?
I hate them.
>> Okay.
>> They are an interruption to my
experience. I'm watching a beautiful
video
of maybe some animals in the wild or I'm
looking at some Bollywood songs,
whatever it is, right?
Suddenly, in less than 5 minutes,
my experience is stopped
and I'm shown a stupid ad that I don't
care about.
And then I'm looking at when is the skip
now button appears.
>> Do Do you have an ad blocker?
>> I have an ad blocker, but ad blocker
does not do the blocking of some of
these streaming companies, right? So,
and if I don't you
the choice is either I pay money
to keep the ads out or I suffer the ads.
What does it tell you?
>> Mhm.
>> That advertisements are disliked by
consumers so much so that these
platforms are telling you, "Hey, you
know what?
If you don't want these ads, you pay me
money." That's like blackmail. An
average consumer is bombarded anywhere
between 3,000 and 10,000 ads every
single day.
The human brain cannot process that
amount of data.
So, the brain has learned to tune out
all these ads. So, you're throwing ads
at the consumers, but they're not even
noticing it. Why would advertising be
the right model for us to communicate?
The need to communicate with the
consumers doesn't go away.
But, the way we are communicating is not
great.
And if I'm getting some results, how do
I know that these results are happening
because of my campaign advertising
campaign? It could happen in spite of
it. It could happen because the gasoline
prices have come down and consumer
behavior So, the attribution mechanisms
are extremely weak.
>> know the platforms are telling you that
the ads are working and you can
>> what they have to tell, right? To sell
more. But, for us as marketers, we need
to understand is this attribution model
really reliable? So, I cut down my
advertising budget by 70%. It is true
till now.
It's not just done once.
We have taken permanently 70% of our
advertising dollars out. Nothing
happened to the business that is
negative.
>> But, you reinvested those dollars.
>> I reinvested those dollars into other
areas like experience
experiential marketing, for example, or
new platforms. We started something
called priceless.com. We have invested
in other areas
and that actually has given us
disproportionate returns. Now, for
example, as a result of which, if you
look at Brand Z
in the past, we used to be at number 87.
>> So, Brand Z is a kind of a measure of of
how much consumers like brands, right?
>> rate the most valuable brands for
>> brands, right.
>> Right. MasterCard used to be the 87th
most valuable brand. Today, it is the
12th most
valuable brand. So, we have been
outpacing our competition whose budgets
were substantially higher than ours big
time. And that trend continues to date.
>> And do you think that's maybe why
marketing has a bit of a trust problem
in the C-suite?
>> Uh marketing has a trust problem for
multiple reasons.
Now, I managed P&Ls and businesses
before I became a CMO. Now, in those
roles, marketing used to report to me.
And I would ask them, "Okay, your budget
this month $20 billion.
Tell me what exactly is it getting me
for the business?" Their answer is, "My
awareness has gone up. My net promoter
score has gone up. My brand
predisposition has gone up. Uh or my
reach has increased."
>> Right. None of those are on your balance
sheet.
>> I don't care.
>> Yeah.
>> I want business results. I say, "Tell
me, what is it doing to either the top
line or the bottom line
in an incredible fashion?" Don't give me
some marketing mumbo jumbo. I would get
really impatient, right?
And they literally like deer caught in
headlights.
That is a big problem. Marketers talking
their own jargon, their own language,
and looking at themselves as marketing
specialists as opposed to business
drivers.
A number of CEOs were interviewed in
terms of their confidence in the CMOs
and in the marketing departments.
Shockingly, more than two-thirds of the
CEOs have said they have zero confidence
in their CMOs and in their marketing
departments to drive profitable growth.
Now, that's a disaster. The CMO role in
many companies has been downgraded to
report to somebody who reports to CEO.
>> So like the chief growth officer or the
CRO
>> Exactly. Right. Chief growth officer,
chief revenue officer, chief customer
officer. Now, if you take away
customers, revenue, and growth out of
marketing, what is left behind?
>> Right.
>> Right. It's It's really fluff. So, the
issue is that marketers did not market
themselves well. They did not learn
themselves the new things that are
happening. And now with AI coming in, it
could be even more devastating if these
people don't quickly educate themselves,
come on top. So, some technologists will
now be running
through some bunch of agents the entire
marketing department, which is not how
it has to be.
>> So, AI threatens those marketers, I
guess, for myriad reasons, right? One
because the the thing that used to be
hard to spin up, you can now make a a
thousand creatives in in two seconds on
Meta or whatever.
Um and also with with AI, I imagine that
that means the CFO and the CEO can very
quickly kind of unpick these fluffy
marketing metrics that they're being
thrown at them. So, what's a marketer to
do, I guess?
>> So, there are two things. On the one
hand, AI is probably the single biggest
threat.
But it is also the single biggest
opportunity for marketing to seize and
regain control of the function properly.
Now, AI, yes, you are right, you can
give a prompt and it'll create 10
creatives, 20 creatives, 100 creatives
in a matter of a few minutes. You might
be a gigantic Unilever,
and I might be a tiny corner shop. Now,
both of us give the prompts, and we get
the output. Your output looks exactly
like my output. So, what happens is the
small companies are able to effectively
now compete against the large companies.
Before you realize, it becomes a sea of
sameness. Everyone's output looks
exactly the same. And because marketers
are also
>> you see that now already? Do you see it
when you scroll through your feeds or
>> You won't believe I was doing this
exercise just about a week back. I was
saying, how many campaigns are using
iceberg
uh as a mnemonic?
>> Right.
>> It was more than 100. Suppose AI gave
you a particular campaign which shows
iceberg.
You accepted it, you ran with it.
>> Mhm.
>> Now when I come in and say I want a
thing, it'll first refer to its
training.
It has learned something from you saying
that iceberg works. It gives me iceberg.
I don't know that you have run the same
thing. I say, "Yeah, this looks good."
Accepted. Before you know, hundreds of
people are using this stupid iceberg.
>> And then reinforcing it because hundreds
of people are using it.
>> it. The system is learning. Say, "Then
all right. So if this person asks for
something like this that a lot of it is
below the surface, let me give you
iceberg." Before you know, everyone is
running with iceberg campaigns, which is
ridiculous, right? Now that is the
biggest opportunity for marketers where
when there is that sea of sameness,
original creativity matters. Innovation
and creativity are going to be the
biggest differentiators in this age of
AI. Because that at the end of three
days is human-to-human connection that
sells your products and brands. It is
not just efficient and effective
communication by itself. The
communication is effective because it is
connecting behind the scenes or below
the surface.
>> And now a word from our sponsor LinkedIn
ads to talk about how to cut the bull
spend from your marketing budget.
>> LinkedIn's cut the bull spend campaign
urges marketers to rethink how they
evaluate performance [music] and where
their budgets actually drive impact. I'm
here with Keith Browning, director of
global brand marketing at LinkedIn to
learn [music] more. How do you define
bull spend in practical terms?
>> So I'd say bull spend is really wasted
advertising spend. It's an investment
that leads to a great-looking dashboard.
So the numbers look good, the arrows are
going in the right direction, but really
it's not actually doing anything to to
drive the business forward, so it
doesn't hold up to scrutiny.
>> How does LinkedIn help marketers reduce
waste and increase efficiency in real
terms. [music]
>> On LinkedIn, you don't have to pay for
attention from people who, you know, are
never going to buy from you. But mass
reach works great if you're selling
breakfast cereal, not so much if you're
selling, you know, CRMs. That's really
where LinkedIn is different.
>> And And do you think that's kind of why
we're seeing more of a rise of of kind
of two trends in in marketing? One being
influencer marketing and kind of
co-creation with creators, and the other
being kind of live events and
experiential in this kind of sea of
sameness. We all want to be
>> That's so right. That's so true.
>> That's so true. So, the rise of
influencer marketing is basically
influencer is working as a filter
to me as to what I should even bother or
care
to watch. So, you're utilizing that
mechanism smartly. So, influencer
marketing, I think it'll continue for
some good time.
Till such time, probably, that everyone
becomes an influencer.
And everyone starts creating using AI,
which is not too far down the line. The
other part of it is experiences.
Experiential marketing gives you the
opportunity to immerse the consumers and
tap into all their senses. I call it
multi-sensory marketing. Tap into all
their senses. Once you give that
experience to the consumer, the consumer
will talk about it and becomes
automatically an ambassador of your
brand. And if you invest your money in
amplifying the message of that
particular ambassador to reach more and
more people of that individual only,
you'll get a tremendous reach. And this
was a big hypothesis we started with,
but then it got proved proven extremely
well. So much so that now a massive
amount of our budget is behind
experiences. And
>> Right. So, you even have like
restaurants, you have
>> We have restaurants.
>> You have live music.
>> There are 10 passion areas. For example,
you have got sports. So, sports is one
huge ocean. Likewise, we went into
music. We went into culinary, tourism,
shopping. Each one of these areas we
curate experiences. And that has done a
lot more for our brand than any campaign
has ever done for us.
>> What's What's an example of a new skill
that maybe you've only had to learn
relatively recently that now is kind of
table stakes for marketers in this era?
>> I wrote this book called Quantum
Marketing 5 years back. And in that I
outlined that there are 24 technologies
which are coming at us. AI is a huge
one. But augmented reality is coming.
Multiverses are coming. Even though
they're going through their winter right
now, they will come right back.
Blockchains and cryptocurrencies are
going to play a significant role. 3D
printing and so on. So, each one of
these you need to really understand them
not as a technologist, but you should
understand it enough to see the
possibilities. The rate of
change which is happening is
unbelievable. So, for example, AI every
week there is something new and
something big that's happening.
>> That's another way to be overwhelmed,
right? If you're going to to a event
like [snorts] Cannes this year and
you're being pitched a generative this
and AI-powered this,
how do you figure out what's real?
>> So, I take the help of AI.
>> Okay.
>> So, I go to AI and say, "Look, I'm being
overwhelmed." It will do the filtering.
So, you don't have to be overwhelmed
because your point is so valid, Laura.
Every single day there are so many
emails which are coming. Everyone is
sending. The vendors are sending. And
then there are news articles. And even
if you subscribe to the so-called
experts in the space, they have got tons
of material under which there are links
that you keep going. It's a rabbit hole
after rabbit hole after rabbit hole.
When do you do your real work? I use
Notebook LM.
Uh I like reading a lot, but I just
don't have the bandwidth to read
everything. So, I give tonight whatever
the material I want to be reviewed. And
tomorrow morning I switch on the podcast
by Notebook LM. So, there are two people
who are talking very naturally and they
tell me everything I need to know. It's
stuff like that. Or if there is a book,
new book which has come.
I'll say, "Hey, is there anything
interesting in this book that I need to
understand?"
>> Well, I hope our listeners don't get any
ideas when they listen to this from
start to finish. No summaries allowed.
>> I hope so.
>> [laughter]
>> Um just while we still have you, um
I wanted to to leave our listeners with
um a little bit of advice, particularly
people who are just starting out in
their marketing careers. Also, people
who might be thinking
maybe marketing isn't for me. I know
that there are some stats out there that
that marketing isn't the most popular
degree course out there right now.
>> Exactly. That's true.
>> Why is Why is there a good reason to go
into marketing in 2026?
>> So, I think if you are scared of AI,
you should be very scared if you're in
other functions than marketing.
Because they functions like finance, IT,
uh even human resources, a lot of
functions like payroll and all these
things, they are totally automatable.
And AI can do a fantastic job.
When AI creates this sea of sameness for
all companies,
how do companies differentiate
themselves and succeed in the
marketplace? Marketing is going to help
them.
So, this is the golden era that we are
about to enter as far as marketing is
concerned, number one.
And if you want to see the world,
marketing is by far the best.
>> Mhm.
>> And lastly, I would say that there's
always a joy when you see your thoughts
taking shape in front of you.
Marketers do it day in and day out.
They're thinking up of a campaign, they
release the campaign, and they're
looking at the impact and how consumers
are actually reacting to it. And it is
absolute adrenaline. If you're into
video games and you're competitively,
you know, playing against them,
marketing is a life video game.
Literally, and you're playing with uh
brutally aggressive competitors and with
constraints, with all kinds of hurdles
thrown in your way. It's such a fun
space, and it's a real one. No,
basically, it's not just some abstract
things that you're putting together. Uh
I think marketing is as human as it can
get.
>> Mhm. You don't get that in payroll.
>> No.
>> Thank you so much for joining us on the
CMO Insider podcast.
>> Thank you again, Laura, for having me.
Much appreciated. Thank you.
>> And thank you for joining us. If you
enjoyed this conversation, please do
like and subscribe. And if you want to
read more marketing content, news,
scoops, analysis, you can go to
businessinsider.com.